<metadata xml:lang="en"><Esri><CreaDate>20140716</CreaDate><CreaTime>12061300</CreaTime><ArcGISFormat>1.0</ArcGISFormat><SyncOnce>FALSE</SyncOnce><DataProperties><lineage><Process ToolSource="c:\program files (x86)\arcgis\desktop10.1\ArcToolbox\Toolboxes\Spatial Analyst Tools.tbx\AreaSolarRadiation" Date="20140716" Time="120613" Name="" export="">AreaSolarRadiation P:\geospatial\Research\rkmeente\SOD\Sonoma\Data\GIS\Environment\DEM\sod15m.tif P:\geospatial\Research\rkmeente\SOD\Sonoma\Data\GIS\Environment\SII\arcsii15m.tif 38.37014002897 200 "WithinDay  172 0 24" 14 0.5 NOINTERVAL 1 FROM_DEM 32 8 8 UNIFORM_SKY 0.3 0.5 # # #</Process></lineage><itemProps><itemName Sync="TRUE">sod15msii172a.tif</itemName><itemLocation><linkage Sync="TRUE">file://P:\geospatial\Research\rkmeente\SOD\Sonoma\Data\GIS\Environment\SII\sod15msii172a.tif</linkage><protocol Sync="TRUE">Local Area Network</protocol></itemLocation><nativeExtBox><westBL Sync="TRUE">6359880.999954</westBL><eastBL Sync="TRUE">6449640.999954</eastBL><southBL Sync="TRUE">1840657.000025</southBL><northBL Sync="TRUE">1953601.000025</northBL><exTypeCode Sync="TRUE">1</exTypeCode></nativeExtBox><imsContentType Sync="TRUE">002</imsContentType></itemProps><coordRef><type Sync="TRUE">Projected</type><geogcsn Sync="TRUE">GCS_NAD_1983_2011</geogcsn><csUnits Sync="TRUE">Linear Unit: Foot_US (0.304801)</csUnits><projcsn Sync="TRUE">NAD_1983_StatePlane_California_II_FIPS_0402_Feet_2011</projcsn><peXml Sync="TRUE">&lt;ProjectedCoordinateSystem xsi:type='typens:ProjectedCoordinateSystem' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance' xmlns:xs='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema' xmlns:typens='http://www.esri.com/schemas/ArcGIS/10.1'&gt;&lt;WKT&gt;PROJCS[&amp;quot;NAD_1983_StatePlane_California_II_FIPS_0402_Feet_2011&amp;quot;,GEOGCS[&amp;quot;GCS_NAD_1983_2011&amp;quot;,DATUM[&amp;quot;D_NAD_1983_2011&amp;quot;,SPHEROID[&amp;quot;GRS_1980&amp;quot;,6378137.0,298.257222101]],PRIMEM[&amp;quot;Greenwich&amp;quot;,0.0],UNIT[&amp;quot;Degree&amp;quot;,0.0174532925199433]],PROJECTION[&amp;quot;Lambert_Conformal_Conic&amp;quot;],PARAMETER[&amp;quot;false_easting&amp;quot;,6561666.666666666],PARAMETER[&amp;quot;false_northing&amp;quot;,1640416.666666667],PARAMETER[&amp;quot;central_meridian&amp;quot;,-122.0],PARAMETER[&amp;quot;standard_parallel_1&amp;quot;,38.33333333333334],PARAMETER[&amp;quot;standard_parallel_2&amp;quot;,39.83333333333334],PARAMETER[&amp;quot;latitude_of_origin&amp;quot;,37.66666666666666],UNIT[&amp;quot;Foot_US&amp;quot;,0.3048006096012192]]&lt;/WKT&gt;&lt;XOrigin&gt;-115211800&lt;/XOrigin&gt;&lt;YOrigin&gt;-93821500&lt;/YOrigin&gt;&lt;XYScale&gt;36983428.057351544&lt;/XYScale&gt;&lt;ZOrigin&gt;-100000&lt;/ZOrigin&gt;&lt;ZScale&gt;10000&lt;/ZScale&gt;&lt;MOrigin&gt;-100000&lt;/MOrigin&gt;&lt;MScale&gt;10000&lt;/MScale&gt;&lt;XYTolerance&gt;0.0032808333333333331&lt;/XYTolerance&gt;&lt;ZTolerance&gt;0.001&lt;/ZTolerance&gt;&lt;MTolerance&gt;0.001&lt;/MTolerance&gt;&lt;HighPrecision&gt;true&lt;/HighPrecision&gt;&lt;/ProjectedCoordinateSystem&gt;</peXml></coordRef><RasterProperties><General><PixelDepth Sync="TRUE">32</PixelDepth><HasColormap Sync="TRUE">FALSE</HasColormap><CompressionType Sync="TRUE">None</CompressionType><NumBands Sync="TRUE">1</NumBands><Format Sync="TRUE">TIFF</Format><HasPyramids Sync="TRUE">FALSE</HasPyramids><SourceType Sync="TRUE">continuous</SourceType><PixelType Sync="TRUE">floating point</PixelType><NoDataValue Sync="TRUE">-3.4028235e+038</NoDataValue></General></RasterProperties></DataProperties><SyncDate>20140716</SyncDate><SyncTime>12155900</SyncTime><ModDate>20140716</ModDate><ModTime>12315200</ModTime><scaleRange><minScale>150000000</minScale><maxScale>5000</maxScale></scaleRange><ArcGISProfile>ItemDescription</ArcGISProfile></Esri><mdLang><languageCode value="eng"/><countryCode value="USA" Sync="TRUE"/></mdLang><mdChar><CharSetCd value="004"/></mdChar><mdHrLv><ScopeCd value="005"/></mdHrLv><mdContact><rpOrgName>Watershed Sciences, Inc. (WSI)</rpOrgName><rpCntInfo><cntPhone><voiceNum>503-505-5100</voiceNum><faxNum>503-546-6801</faxNum></cntPhone><cntAddress addressType="physical"><delPoint>421 S.W. 6th Ave., Suite 800</delPoint><city>Portland</city><adminArea>OR</adminArea><postCode>97204</postCode><country>US</country></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="007"/></role></mdContact><mdStanName>ArcGIS Metadata</mdStanName><mdStanVer>1.0</mdStanVer><distInfo><distributor><distorCont><rpOrgName>Sonoma County Agricultural Preservation and Open Space District</rpOrgName><rpCntInfo><cntPhone><voiceNum>(707) 565-7369</voiceNum></cntPhone><cntAddress addressType="both"><delPoint>747 Mendocino Ave, Suite 100</delPoint><city>Santa Rosa</city><adminArea>CA</adminArea><postCode>95401</postCode><country>US</country></cntAddress></rpCntInfo><role><RoleCd value="005"/></role></distorCont></distributor><distFormat><formatName Sync="TRUE">Raster Dataset</formatName></distFormat></distInfo><dataIdInfo><idCitation><date><pubDate>2014-02-19</pubDate></date><citRespParty><rpOrgName>Sonoma County Vegetation Mapping and LiDAR Program</rpOrgName><role><RoleCd value="006"/></role></citRespParty><presForm><PresFormCd value="005"/></presForm><presForm><fgdcGeoform>raster digital data</fgdcGeoform></presForm><resTitle Sync="TRUE">sod15msii172a.tif</resTitle></idCitation><idAbs>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;This solar irradiation surface was calculated in in ArcGIS 10.1 using the 48-foot (~15m) aggregated version (sod15m.tif) of the original bare earth DEM produced by the Sonoma Veg Map program. The Area Solar Radiation tool in ArcGIS was used to calculate the total irradiance (Wh/m^2) based on the 48-foot pixel resolution DEM for the 172nd day of the year (June 21st). &lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;The solar radiation analysis tools calculate insolation across a landscape or for specific locations, based on methods from the hemispherical viewshed algorithm developed by Rich et al. (Rich 1990, Rich et al. 1994) and further developed by Fu and Rich (2000, 2002). The tool settings used were as follows: Latitude (calculated from DEM)=38.37014002897, Sky size=200, Day number of the year=172, Start time=0, End time=24, Hour interval=0.5, Z-factor=1 (not sure if that was correct option), Slope/aspect calculated from DEM, Calculation directions=32, Zenith divisions=8, Azimuth divisions=8, Diffuse model type=UNIFORM_SKY, Diffuse proportion=0.3, Transmittivity=0.5,  Also see Dubayah (1994) for further applications of modeling solar radiation, wherein he describes how direct irradiance is calcualted as the cosine of the solar illumination angle on the slope with the optical depth (transmissivity) assuming a constant value. The specified coordinate system for this dataset is California State Plane Zone II (FIPS 0402), NAD83 (2011), with units in US Survey Feet for horizontal, and vertical units are NAVD88 (12A) US Survey Feet.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</idAbs><idPurp>This is a surface to serve as an index for potential solar radiation across the Sonoma County sudden oak death study area during the 172nd day of the year (summer solstice). It was derived from original data provided by the Sonoma County Vegetation Mapping and LiDAR Program (http://sonomavegmap.org) and the University of Maryland (under grant NNX13AP69G from NASA’s Carbon Monitoring System, Dr. Ralph Dubayah, PI) contracted LiDAR and orthophoto data collection for all of Sonoma County in late 2013. Also included in the data collection were two areas in Mendocino County - the Soda Spring Creek-Dry Creek Watershed and Lake Mendocino. This fine scale data will help provide an accurate, up-to-date inventory of the county’s landscape features, ecological communities and habitats. Project funders include: NASA, the University of Maryland, the Sonoma County Agricultural Preservation and Open Space District, the Sonoma County Water Agency, the California Department of Fish and Wildlife, the United States Geological Survey, the Sonoma County Information Systems Department, the Sonoma County Transportation and Public Works Department, the Nature Conservancy, and the City of Petaluma.</idPurp><idCredit>Sonoma County Vegetation Mapping and LiDAR Consortium, NASA, University of Maryland, Watershed Sciences, Inc., Tukman Geospatial LLC. 
Kasten, F. (1996). The Linke turbidity factor based on improved values of the integral Rayleigh optical thickness. Solar Energy, 56 (3), 239-244. Dubayah RC. Modeling a solar radiation topoclimatology for the Rio Grande River Basin. J Veg Sci. 1994;5(5):627-640. doi:10.2307/3235879.</idCredit><idStatus><ProgCd value="001"/></idStatus><resMaint><maintFreq><MaintFreqCd value="011"/></maintFreq></resMaint><placeKeys><keyword>Sonoma County, Lake Mendocino, Sonoma Lake Watershed</keyword></placeKeys><themeKeys><keyword>LiDAR, Light Detection And Ranging</keyword></themeKeys><searchKeys><keyword>LiDAR</keyword><keyword>Light Detection And Ranging</keyword><keyword>Sonoma County</keyword><keyword>Lake Mendocino</keyword><keyword>Sonoma Lake Watershed</keyword></searchKeys><resConst><LegConsts><useLimit>Data were provided by the University of Maryland and the Sonoma County Vegetation Mapping and LiDAR Program (http://sonomavegmap.org) under grant NNX13AP69G from NASA’s Carbon Monitoring System (Dr. Ralph Dubayah, PI). This data is available for unrestricted public use. However, users should acknowledge the source of the data in any reports, publications, or presentations where the data is used.</useLimit></LegConsts></resConst><resConst><Consts><useLimit>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;Data were provided by the University of Maryland and the Sonoma County Vegetation Mapping and LiDAR Program (http://sonomavegmap.org) under grant NNX13AP69G from NASA’s Carbon Monitoring System (Dr. Ralph Dubayah, PI). This data is available for unrestricted public use. However, users should acknowledge the source of the data in any reports, publications, or presentations where the data is used.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</useLimit></Consts></resConst><dataLang><languageCode value="eng"/><countryCode value="USA" Sync="TRUE"/></dataLang><dataExt><exDesc>Ground Condition - LiDAR: Leica ALS50 &amp; Leica ALS70</exDesc><tempEle><TempExtent><exTemp><TM_Period><tmBegin>2013-09-28</tmBegin><tmEnd>2013-11-26</tmEnd></TM_Period></exTemp></TempExtent></tempEle></dataExt><dataExt><geoEle><GeoBndBox><westBL>-123.238581</westBL><eastBL>-122.390681</eastBL><southBL>38.298129</southBL><northBL>38.511668</northBL></GeoBndBox></geoEle></dataExt><envirDesc Sync="TRUE">Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.1.1.3143</envirDesc><spatRpType><SpatRepTypCd value="002" Sync="TRUE"/></spatRpType><dataExt><geoEle xmlns=""><GeoBndBox esriExtentType="search"><exTypeCode Sync="TRUE">1</exTypeCode><westBL Sync="TRUE">-122.705333</westBL><eastBL Sync="TRUE">-122.389893</eastBL><northBL Sync="TRUE">38.525945</northBL><southBL Sync="TRUE">38.214335</southBL></GeoBndBox></geoEle></dataExt></dataIdInfo><dqInfo><dqScope><scpLvl><ScopeCd value="005"/></scpLvl></dqScope><report type="DQConcConsis"><measDesc>LiDAR flight lines have been examined to ensure that there was at least 60% sidelap, there are no gaps between flightlines, and overlapping flightlines have consistent elevation values. Shaded relief images have been visually inspected for data errors such as pits, border artifacts, gaps, and shifting. The data were examined at a 1:3000 scale.</measDesc></report><report type="DQCompOm"><measDesc>LiDAR has been collected and processed for all areas within the project study Area. In some areas of heavy vegetation and forest cover, there may be relatively few ground points in the LiDAR data. Some elevation units have been interpolated across areas in the ground model where there are no elevation data (e.g., over water, over dense vegetation). TINing the points produces large triangles and hence the elevations may be less accurate within such areas. Some elevation units have been interpolated across areas in the ground model where there are no elevation data (e.g., over water, over dense vegetation).</measDesc></report><report type="DQAbsExtPosAcc" dimension="horizontal"><measDesc>Relative Accuracy measures the divergence between points from different flightlines. Relative Accuracy median is 0.05 meters (0.17 feet) out of 106,255,686,985 laser points over 4,133 flightlines. For more information regarding the internal consistency between ground-classified points from different overlapping flightlines please see LiDAR data report.</measDesc></report><report type="DQAbsExtPosAcc" dimension="vertical"><measDesc>The Fundamental Vertical Accuracy (FVA) of the data set is 0.03 meters (0.09 feet). Accuracy was assessed using 9,685 ground control points (GCP). These ground control points are distributed through out the project study area.</measDesc><evalMethDesc>The FVA was tested using 851 independent ground control points (GCPs) located in open terrain. The GCPs were distributed throughout the project area. Elevations from the unclassified LiDAR surface were measured for the x,y location of each check point. Elevations interpolated from the LiDAR surface were then compared to the elevation values of the surveyed control. The Root-Mean-Square (RMSE) was computed to be 0.03 m (0.09 ft.). AccuracyZ has been tested to meet 0.05 m (0.17 ft.) FVA at 95 Percent confidence level using RMSE(z) x 1.9600 as defined by the National Standards for Spatial Data Accuracy (NSSDA); assessed and reported using National Digital Elevation Program (NDEP)/ASRPS Guidelines.</evalMethDesc><measResult><QuanResult><quanVal>0.05 meters RMSEz at 95 percent Confidence Interval.</quanVal></QuanResult></measResult></report><dataLineage><prcStep><stepDesc>Acquisition. LiDAR data acquisition was started September 28, 2013 and was completed on November 26, 2013. The survey is utilizing a Leica ALS50 or ALS70 laser system mounted in a Piper Navajo PA-31-325 or Cessna Caravan 208B. Near nadir scan angles were used to increase penetration of vegetation to ground surfaces. Ground level GPS and aircraft IMU were collected during the flight.</stepDesc><stepDateTm>2014-02-19</stepDateTm></prcStep><prcStep><stepDesc>LiDAR Data Processing. Flight lines and data were reviewed to ensure complete coverage of the study area and positional accuracy of the laser points. Laser point return coordinates were computed using ALS Post Processor software and IPAS Pro GPS/INS software, based on independent data from the LiDAR system, IMU, and aircraft. The raw LiDAR file was assembled into flight lines per return with each point having an associated x, y, and z coordinate. Visual inspection of swath to swath laser point consistencies within the study area were used to perform manual refinements of system alignment. Custom algorithms were designed to evaluate points between adjacent flight lines. Automated system alignment was computed based upon randomly selected swath to swath accuracy measurements that consider elevation, slope, and intensities. Specifically, refinement in the combination of system pitch, roll and yaw offset parameters optimize internal consistency. Noise (e.g., pits and birds) was filtered using ALS post-processing software, based on known elevation ranges and included the removal of any cycle slips. Using TerraScan and MicroStation, ground classifications utilized custom settings appropriate to the study area. The corrected and filtered return points were compared to the RTK ground survey points collected to verify the vertical and horizontal accuracies. Points were output as laser points, TINed and GRIDed surfaces.</stepDesc><stepDateTm>2014-10-24</stepDateTm></prcStep></dataLineage></dqInfo><spatRepInfo><Georect><axisDimension type="002"><dimSize Sync="TRUE">1870</dimSize><dimResol><value Sync="TRUE" uom="Foot_US">48.000000</value></dimResol></axisDimension><axisDimension type="001"><dimSize Sync="TRUE">2353</dimSize><dimResol><value Sync="TRUE" uom="Foot_US">48.000000</value></dimResol></axisDimension><cellGeo><CellGeoCd Sync="TRUE" value="002"/></cellGeo><numDims Sync="TRUE">2</numDims><tranParaAv Sync="TRUE">1</tranParaAv><chkPtAv Sync="TRUE">0</chkPtAv><cornerPts><pos Sync="TRUE">6359880.999954 1840657.000025</pos></cornerPts><cornerPts><pos Sync="TRUE">6359880.999954 1953601.000025</pos></cornerPts><cornerPts><pos Sync="TRUE">6449640.999954 1953601.000025</pos></cornerPts><cornerPts><pos Sync="TRUE">6449640.999954 1840657.000025</pos></cornerPts><centerPt><pos Sync="TRUE">6404760.999954 1897129.000025</pos></centerPt><ptInPixel><PixOrientCd Sync="TRUE" value="001"/></ptInPixel></Georect></spatRepInfo><contInfo><ImgDesc><covDim><Band><valUnit><UOM type="length"/></valUnit><dimDescrp Sync="TRUE">Band_1</dimDescrp><maxVal Sync="TRUE">6406.979004</maxVal><minVal Sync="TRUE">2716.120605</minVal><bitsPerVal Sync="TRUE">32</bitsPerVal></Band></covDim><contentTyp><ContentTypCd Sync="TRUE" value="001"/></contentTyp></ImgDesc></contInfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>This raster data set represents ground surface elevations derived from ground classified LiDAR point data.</eaover><eadetcit>Sonoma County Vegetation Mapping and LiDAR Program</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><mdHrLvName Sync="TRUE">dataset</mdHrLvName><refSysInfo><RefSystem><refSysID><identCode code="0" Sync="TRUE"/></refSysID></RefSystem></refSysInfo><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20140716</mdDateSt></metadata>
